TED：吸引力的科学
The science of attraction
We like to think of romantic feelings as spontaneous
我们总认为恋爱的感觉是不可预测
and indescribable things that come from the heart.
无法形容的心理感受
But it's actually your brain running a complex
但其实那是你的脑袋在数秒之间
series of calculations within a matter of seconds
处理一连串复杂的计算
that's responsible for determining attraction.
最后决定了什么对你有吸引力
Doesn't sound quite as poetic, does it?
听起来一点也不浪漫，对吧？
But just because the calculations are happening in your brain
但就算你脑袋里转着计算公式
doesn't mean those warm, fuzzy feelings are all in your head.
不代表那个温热柔软的感觉
都只是你的幻觉
In fact, all five of your senses play a role,
事实上，你的五个感官也各出了一份力
each able to vote for, or veto, a budding attraction.
投票通过或否决刚滋长的爱苗
The eyes are the first components in attraction.
眼睛是参与吸引力决策
的第一个成员
Many visual beauty standards vary
视觉审美标准在各文化、时代之间皆相异
between cultures and eras,
视觉审美标准在
各文化、时代之间皆相异
and signs of youth, fertility and good health,
年轻、生育力
与健康的征象也都不同
such as long lustrous hair,
例如有光泽的长长秀发
or smooth, scar-free skin,
或光滑无痕的肌肤
are almost always in demand
几乎总是需求不断
because they're associated with reproductive fitness.
因为这些和繁衍后代的能力有关
And when the eyes spot something they like,
而当眼睛看见喜欢的事物时
our instinct is to move closer
我们的本能便是靠上前
so the other senses can investigate.
好让其他的感官也能够侦察
The nose's contribution to romance
鼻子对于爱情的贡献
is more than noticing perfume or cologne.
不只是注意到香水或古龙水而已
It's able to pick up on natural chemical signals
鼻子也接收自然化学物质的信号
known as pheromones.
这类物质称作费洛蒙
These not only convey important
费洛蒙不只传达关于其来源的
physical or genetic information about their source
生理或基因的重要信息
but are able to activate a physiological
也能引发信号接受者
or behavioral response in the recipient.
在生理上或行为上的回应
In one study, a group of women at different points in their ovulation cycles
某研究曾让一群
在月经周期不同阶段的女人
wore the same t-shirts for three nights.
穿着同一件衣服三晚
After male volunteers were randomly assigned
再随机指定男性自愿者
to smell either one of the worn shirts,
闻那些被穿过的衣服
or a new unworn one,
或是没人穿过的新衣服之后
saliva samples showed an increase in testosterone
唾液采样显示
闻排卵期女性穿过衣物的男性
in those who had smelled a shirt worn by an ovulating woman.
身上睪固酮量增加了
Such a testosterone boost
这样的睪固酮激增
may give a man the nudge to persue a woman
就可能驱使男人去追求一位
he might not have otherwise noticed.
他原来也许不会注意到的女人
A woman's nose is particularly attuned
女人的鼻子则对
to MHC molecules,
主要组织兼容性复合体 (MHC) 分子特别敏锐
which are used to fight disease.
这是用来抗病的分子
In this case, opposites attract.
在这种情形下，异性就会相吸
When a study asked women to smell t-shirts
当实验要求女人闻
that had been worn by different men,
不同男人穿过的 T 恤时
they preferred the odors of those whose
她们偏好与自己
MHC molecules differed from theirs.
不同 MHC 分子的气味
This makes sense.
这不无道理
Genes that result in a greater variety of immunities
免疫能力多元的基因
may give offspring a major survival advantage.
可能给后代重要的存活优势
Our ears also determine attraction.
我们的耳朵也能决定吸引力
Men prefer females with high-pitched, breathy voices,
男人比较喜欢女人的声音频率高、气声多
and wide formant spacing,
共振峰间距宽
correlated with smaller body size.
代表了较小的体形
While women prefer low-pitched voices
而女人则偏爱低频的声音
with a narrow formant spacing
共振峰间距窄
that suggest a larger body size.
表示体形较大
And not surprisingly,
以及，意料之中
touch turns out to be crucial for romance.
触觉对爱情来说是很关键的
In this experiment,
在这个研究中
not realizing the study had begun,
不知实验已开始的受试者
participants were asked to briefly hold the coffee,
被要求暂时拿着一杯咖啡
either hot or iced.
可能是冰的也可能是热的
Later, the participants read a story
之后，受试者阅读一篇故事
about a hypothetical person,
内容关于一个虚构的人物
and were asked to rate their personality.
他们被要求评价这个人物的个性
Those who had held the hot cup of coffee
拿着热咖啡的人
perceived the person in the story as happier,
对故事人物认知为较开心
more social, more generous and better-natured
也较愿意交际、大方，较温和的人
than those who had held the cup of iced coffee,
比照拿冰咖啡的受试者的看法
who rated the person as cold, stoic, and unaffectionate.
他们则认为这个人物冷漠、严谨、不热情
If a potential mate has managed to pass
如果有某个可能的对象通过
all these tests, there's still one more:
这些检验，最后还有一项：
the infamous first kiss,
恶名昭彰的初吻
a rich and complex exchange
初吻交换丰富而复杂的
of tactile and chemical cues,
触觉及化学信号
such as the smell of one's breath,
像是呼吸的气味
and the taste of their mouth.
及嘴巴的味道
This magical moment is so critical
这个神奇的时刻非常关键
that a majority of men and women
以致于很多男人女人
have reported losing their attraction to someone
都说过他们在糟糕的初吻经验后
after a bad first kiss.
就对对方失去兴趣了
Once attraction is confirmed,
一旦确认了吸引力
your bloodstream is flooded
你的血液里便充满了
with norepinephrine,
去甲肾上腺素
activating your fight or flight system.
启动你的「打或逃」机制
Your heart beats faster,
你的心跳加速
your pupils dilate,
瞳孔放大
and your body releases glucose for additional energy,
身体释放出葡萄糖
以产生额外的能量
not because you're in danger
不是因为你有危险了
but because your body is telling you
而是你的身体在告诉你
that something important is happening.
有件大事正在发生
To help you focus,
为了让你能专注
norepinephrine creates a sort of tunnel vision,
去甲肾上腺素制造出隧道视觉的效果
blocking out surrounding distractions,
遮蔽周遭让你分心的东西
possibly even warping your sense of time,
可能甚至涷结你的时间感
and enhancing your memory.
而增强你的记忆力
This might explain why people never forget their first kiss.
这也许能解释为何人们总忘不了初吻
The idea of so much of our attraction
知道了我们的吸引力
being influenced by chemicals and evolutionary biology
是如此受化学物质与生物演化的影响
may seem cold and scientific rather than romantic,
可能令人感觉无情、过于理性，一点也不浪漫
but the next time you see someone you like,
但下次你遇见喜欢的人时
try to appreciate how your entire body is playing matchmaker
试着感谢你的整个身体如何替你作媒
to decide if that beautiful stranger is right for you.
来决定这个美丽的陌生人适不适合你